Register of the Okhrana records
Hoover Institution Archives
- IX. Overt activities (Boxes 65-90)
  - a. Newspaper service, clippings, collection of overt information (Boxes 65-89)
    The overt collection of information was an important task of the Okhrana abroad. Detailed expense accounts through the years show that agents, case officers, and Paris Office employees were purchasing leftist newspapers and other publications. Cover memoranda to Headquarters submitted these published materials weekly, usually without comments. Agents in the field attached to their reports pertinent clippings, while the Paris Office, using such overt materials as supplements to classified reports, kept collecting the clippings in general albums and in folders on specific intelligence topics.
    It is possible that some of the collections of newspaper clippings were lost or discarded during the emergency move of the archives to Bordeaux when Paris was in danger of being taken by the German army. A set of 22 large albums, covering the period from 1902 to 1905, is organized in chronological order for French clippings. The selection of clippings ia general, including political, economic, and international topics, but without annotations or guides to numbered pages. Emphasis in this collection was made also on such matters as foreign reporting on events in Russia and émigré activities.
    One large album, clippings on Burtsev's exposure of Garting, is of particular interest. Clippings collected from the leftist press and spokesmen for the revolutionary cause are suggestive of the methods used by revolutionary counter-intelligence to penetrate the Okhrana and employ defectors.
    Other collections of clippings cover such topics as revolutionary activities in general, the attitudes of the French press toward the imperial family, the French Sûreté Générale, the Beilis case (an anti-Jewish trial in Russia), and the Tsar's Manifesto of 1903.
    - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office referring to press service, publisher information, publications, etc., 1907-1917 (Index IXa, Folder 1a)
    - Cover notes for newspapers and clippings sent to and from Headquarters, 1902-1916 (Index IXa, Folder 1b)
    - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office regarding newspapers and publications, 1894-1916 (Index IXa, Folder 1c)
    - Manifest of Jewish anarchists, 1916 (Index IXa, Folder 1d)
    - Kropotkin's letter to Professor Stefan, 1914 (Index IXa, Folder 1e)
    - Report on the convention of the Grand Eastern Masonic Lodge in Paris, 1914 (Index IXa, Folder 1f)
    - Dispatches on cooperation between German Social Democrats and Russian revolutionaries, 1915 (Index IXa, Folder 1g)
    - Polish question in the press, 1913-1915 (Index IXa, Folder 1h)
    - Collection of newspaper clippings on the visit of the Russian war fleet in French ports, 1893 (Index IXa, Folder 1i)
    - Clippings from French, Swiss, and English newspapers referring to revolutionaries, 1906-1914 (Index IXa, Folder 2a)
    - Clippings from French newspapers on the Russian imperial family, 1912-1914 (Index IXa, Folder 2b)
    - Clippings from French and Swiss newspapers on Russian matters not sent to Headquarters, 1913-1916 (Index IXa, Folder 2c)
    - Clippings from French newspapers on the French Sûreté, 1913-1914 (Index IXa, Folder 3a)
    - Clippings from French newspapers on the exploitation of Russian workers in coal mines in northern France, 1913 (Index IXa, Folder 3b)
    - Clippings from French and Swiss newspapers referring to the Beilis case, 1914 (Index IXa, Folder 3c)
    - Scrapbook with a collection of clippings from Le Matin by Rirette-Maitrejean (Index IXa, Folder 3d)
    - Clippings from English, French and Russian newspapers on the Tsar's manifesto in 1903 (Index IXa, Folder 3e)
    - Scrapbooks of French newspaper clippings on various Russian matters, 1902-1905
      Available on microfilm reels 135-140
      - 1902 October 21-December 31 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 135
        Topics include: penetration of armed forces in Russia; an uprising in Macedonia; Russia and England's fight for Afghanistan; Finland; and Vladimir Lamzdorf's mission to Austria and the Balkans.
      - 1903 January 1-March 4 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: constitutionalism in Russia; war movements in the Balkans and Dardanelles; Russia's preliminary budget for 1903; and Finland.
      - 1903 March 5-May 16 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the Tsar's manifesto; crisis in the Balkans; Gots's arrest in Italy; student unrest; assassinations; the workers' movement; pogroms; and Poland.
      - 1903 May 17-July 29 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 136
        Topics include: pogroms in Russia; war preparations in Asia; attacks on Roosevelt for his stand against the pogroms; and Georges Clemenceau.
      - 1903 July 30-October 13 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: strikes in Russia; Russian interests in the Far East; Kishinev pogrom; Witte dismissed; revolutionary movement; pogroms; Tsar in Vienna; and internal troubles in Russia.
      - 1903 October 13-December 31 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the Russo-Japanese conflict; the pogrom in Gomel; Armenian revolutionaries; and reforms in Russia.
      - 1904 January 1-28 June (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the crisis in the Far East; incident at the Avenue de Choisy where four Okhrana agents were exposed; Grigorii Gershuni's letter after his death sentence; August Bebel; revolutionary propaganda in the Russian army; Burtsev; revolution in Poland; and Bobrikov's assassination by Eugen Schauman.
      - 1904 (special album on Burtsev's exposure of Garting) (Index IXa, Folder 4)
      - 1904 June 29-August 10 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 137
        Topics include: internal troubles in Russia; and the assassination of Pleve.
      - 1904 August 11-October 31 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the Congress of the French Socialist Party; Congress of the Russian Social Revolutionaries in Amsterdam; Manasevich-Manuilov exposed as an Okhrana agent; Tsar's manifesto; Sazonov's escape; students and the Russian police; and the Russian army.
      - 1904 November 1-December 27 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: Russian socialists; the agrarian problem; anti-Semitism; and trial of Sazonov and Sikorskii for the assassination of Pleve.
      - 1904 December 28-December 22 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the revolution in Russia; the Tsar's manifeso; Tolstoy's letter to the Tsar; Sazonov's trial; Father Gapon; and a general strike in Russia.
      - 1905 January 22-27 January (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 138
        Topics include: revolutionaries in Russia; Father Gapon; bloody demonstrations in Petrograd; the role played by Japanese money; and Russians in Paris.
      - 1905 January 28-February 4 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: speeches by Anatole France; Plekhanov; Gorky; and Struve.
      - 1905 February 5-18 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
      - 1905 February 18-March 1 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the assassination of Grand Duke Sergei; revolutionary action in Poland and Russia; Father Gapon; and Gorky.
      - 1905 March 2-21 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 139
        Topics include: terrorists in Russia; Father Gapon; revolts in the Caucasus and Poland; Gorky's release from prison; anarchists and nihilists; Bernhard von Bélow; Jews in the Russian revolution; and Georges Clemenceau on Poland.
      - 1905 March 22-April 28 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: a school strike in Poland; Father Gapon; and Russian revolution.
      - 1905 June 13-July 8 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: events in Yalta, Warsaw, and Lodz; zemstvos; Kaliaev's letter to the widow of Grand Duke Sergei; Social-Democratic appeal to Russian soldiers; Russian peasants; Jean Jaurés on the revolution; and the Potemkin mutiny.
      - 1905 July 9-25 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the Potemkin mutiny; armed forces affected by revolutionary slogans; assassination of Pavel Shuvalov; revolutionary action in Russia, Poland, and Armenia; the Jews and the revolution; zemstvos; internal troubles of Russia; and the meeting of the Tsar and Kaiser Wilhelm II.
      - 1905 July 25-August 16 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the Tsar's meeting with Kaiser Wilhelm II; Potemkin mutiny; England; Zionism; the Bund; and plans for a general assembly in Russia
      - 1905 August 17-29 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Topics include: the Duma; Potemkin mutiny; revolution in Poland; interests of Russia and England in Persia; and the constitutional movement.
      - 1905 August 29-June 12 (Index IXa, Folder 4)
        Available on microfilm reel 140
        Topics include: the situation in Poland and Finland; Kaliaev's trial and sentence; Father Gapon; Struve's correspondence with Jaurés.
  - b. Influencing local press (Box 66)
    The Paris Okhrana always had the interest and apparently the means of exerting some influence on the press abroad, but two periods in its existence stand out as particularly active and significant in this respect. By the 1890s, Chief Rachkovskii had developed a close contact with Jules Hansen, a correspondent with wide access to the press and to important government officials, leading to much publicity on the emerging Franco-Russian alliance and to increased cooperation with the Sûreté against the revolutionaries. Hansen was the recipient of Okhrana funds, but the records are vague or nonexistent regarding the total expenses in this form of the Okhrana's political action.
    Similarly, in the case of Manasevich-Manuilov, the Okhrana's staff agent in Paris during the first few years of the century, it is difficult to deduce the amount of funds used by him for the purpose of influencing the foreign press. That was his assignment in Paris in 1902, when he was rated as a political rather than an intelligence agent. In addition to developing contacts with high officials in government and diplomatic missions, his tasks consisted of influencing the press, providing for releases and modifying editorial policies.
    Folder 1 of this collection contains mostly correspondence with Headquarters concerning contacts with the foreign press, drafts of prepared articles, subsidies, etc. Folder. No. 2 concerns Manasevich-Manuilov's liasion to Paris with regard to contacts with the French press.
    Available on microfilm reel 134
    - Correspondence between Headquarters and the Paris office pertaining to contacts with the foreign press and influencing the selection of news on Russia, 1893-1915 (Index IXb, Folder 1a)
    - Articles, clippings, and translations published in the foreign press, 1891-1915 (Index IXb, Folder 1b)
    - Correspondence pertaining to subsidies for the French press, 1889-1911 (Index IXb, Folder 1c)
    - Consideration by Headquarters for a subsidy for Parizhskii vestnik (Index IXb, Folder 1d)
    - Reports on the activities of Trofimov in England, 1915 (Index IXb, Folder 1e)
    - Coverage of the Rips trial by the French press, 1910 (Index IXb, Folder 1f)
    - Notes and letters of instruction to Manasevich-Manuilov on his Paris mission to establish contacts with the French press and influence publication of news about Russia, 1902-1904 (Index IXb, Folder 2)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram, March 5, 1903, re influencing the Nouvelle Revue, in XIIIb(2), folder 2 (Index IXb, Folder 3)
    - Reference: See incoming telegram, March 31, 1904, on payment for 100 subscriptions to Gaulois, in XIIIc(3), folder 16 (Index IXb, Folder 4)
    - Reference: See incoming telegram, June 18, 1904, with approval for the purchase of subscriptions to Le Gaulois and Le Figaro, in XIIIc(3), folder 16 (Index IXb, Folder 5)
    - Reference: See incoming telegram, June 21, 1905, concerning the necessity of "warning" the French public against a French correspondent writing unfavorable articles, in XIIIc(3), folder 18 (Index IXb, Folder 6)
    - Reference: See incoming telegram, June 1, 1905, with instructions for press releases to newspapers concerning disorder on the Potemkin, in XIIIc(3), folder 18 (Index IXb, Folder 7)
  - c. Cooperation with Russian missions abroad (Box 90)
    As the documents in this small collection indicate, contacts of Okhrana representatives with diplomatic, consular, and other Russian missions abroad was considered undesirable, if not expressly forbidden. Under Vg, the documents related to actual liaison for purposes of exchanging information, required particularly in war days or in cases of checking on the loyalty of employees and applicants for visas and passports. Under this index, the documents deal chiefly with overt matters. It is interesting to note that missions abroad used the normal diplomatic channels, communicating with their home office, which referred the matter to Okhrana Headquarters, where, in turn, the case was submitted to the Okhrana representative in the field.
    - Dispatches and notes of the cooperation with diplomatic and consular missions in overt matters, 1906-1916 (Index IXc, Folder 1)
      See also the collection under Vg.
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index IXc, Folder 2)
  - d. General services, favors (Box 90)
    The first four folders hold a few dispatches and many letters referring to general matters of no operational or intelligence significance. The letters are mostly requests for various favors or expressions of thanks therefore, inquiries about addresses or welfare of individuals, denunciations among émigrés, and the like. In the Folder 5 there is a batch of some few hundred calling cards and an equal number of picture post cards addressed mostly to Okhrana personnel and kept as souvenirs.
    Available on microfilm reels 140-141
    - Letters from Headquarters concerning general services, 1881-1916 (Index IXd, Folder 1)
    - Letters on various matters in general services, 1881-1917 (Index IXd, Folder 2)
    - Reports on Russian workers at the Auby mines, 1913 (Index IXd, Folder 3)
    - Undated letters on various matters (Index IXd, Folder 4)
      Available on microfilm reel 141
    - Miscellaneous documents including a pack of calling cards, picture postcards, 2 notebooks of Rosenkrantz (1890), etc. (Index IXd, Folder 5)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index IXd, Folder 6)
- X. Operational techniques (Boxes 91-101)
  - a. Agent documentation (Box 91)
    The Okhrana enjoyed special status in matters of obtaining passports and other travel documents for the use of its agents. It had the facilities and contacts with the issuing authorities at home and abroad, and it could arrange for the passports to read in any pseudonym chosen for an agent's use. The passports and communications about them show that an agent could be given two passports at the same time, for instance, one for use in Russia, and another one for abroad. The dispatches also show that the Okhrana abroad was supplied with blank passports, to be used at its discretion or at the discretion of the case officers.
    As one set of documents shows, agents were given briefing instructions on the use of passports in connection with foreign resident requirements in France and other countries. In addition to the required briefing of the agents with extra-legal passports, the Okhrana also informed such organs as the border controls about the nature and authority of any passport that might otherwise come under suspicion.
    The documents in this collection are included mostly as samples, in order to give a comprehensive picture of the methods of agent documentation.
    - Passport for agent Simon Zilberstein ("Aleks"), 1906 (Index Xa, Folder 1)
    - Passport for agent Herzig, under the name of Bekchiev, 1908 (Index Xa, Folder 2)
    - Passport for Okhrana office employee Fedorova in Paris, 1914 (Index Xa, Folder 3)
    - Passport issued in Vitebsk for agent Model, 1914 (Index Xa, Folder 4)
    - 22 Russian passports (Index Xa, Folder 5)
    - Letters of documentation for agent Neuhaus, 1911-1912 (Index Xa, Folder 6)
    - Briefing materials on passport and foreign resident requirements in France, 1914 (Index Xa, Folder 7)
    - Special passes for agents, some signed by Durnovo, 1910 (Index Xa, Folder 8)
    - Dispatches pertaining to the use of passports in secret Okhrana operations, 1903-1913 (Index Xa, Folder 9)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Xa, Folder 10)
  - b. Control of photographic studios in Paris (Box 91)
    The Okhrana in Paris never succeeded with the requests to establish a photographic section of its own. Principal agent Marcel Bittard-Monin, upon the Okhrana's request, went so far as to collect all necessary data on photographic equipment and costs, but an Okhrana photo shop was never set up. Headquarters and area subdivisions were equipped with police-type laboratories, as the assortments of pictures on file from their rogue (revolutionary) galleries indicate.
    The extensive photographic file (see boxes under XIIIf(4)) was the product of constant collection. Many photos of revolutionaries came from Headquarters files. Another sizeable collection was gathered in the field, particularly through the control of, or less formal contact with, various photographic studios in Paris and elsewhere. In the pictorial files of the Okhrana are many sets of pictures obtained from studios catering to Russian émigré groups.
    - Letter to Ambassador from Photo-Malivert offering their services, 1905 (Index Xb, Folder 1a)
    - Documents concerning the cost of equipment for photographic studios in the Paris Okhrana office, 1909 (Index Xb, Folder 1b)
    - Dispatch concerning extra copies of photographs of revolutionaries from St. Petersburg, 1910 (Index Xb, Folder 1c)
    - Letter from Paris photographic studio announcing a change of address, 1912 (Index Xb, Folder 1d)
    - Reference: For information on the Laizier photographic studio in Paris, 1914, see IIIe, folder 3 (Index Xb, Folder 2)
    - Reference: See the personal dossier of Henri Ozanne, who was hired in 1908 for his photographic services, in IIIe, folder 3 (Index Xb, Folder 3)
  - c. Censorship and perlustration (Boxes 91-92)
    The only systematic and fairly continuous censorship of mails was developed by the Paris Okhrana in an area of coastal resort towns of the Italian Riviera. Its non-Russian agents succeeded in engaging some postal officials to "lend" them the mail (at the rate of five francs per letter) for overnight use and perlustration (exact copy with a transparent overlay). If such helping service was achieved in Paris or other parts, it was only occasionally and with the help of accommodating concierges rather than postal employees.
    Before modern photocopying, perlustration was a method of considerable advantage. Copyists were able to reproduce the "hand" of the writer, leaving no telling mark on the original, with envelopes (use of steam for opening) resealed expertly and without traces of added glue. In 1909, the Paris Office requested the establishment of a photographic darkroom for copying of correspondence, but no such section was ever added.
    Folder 1 of this collection is an assortment of perlustrated letters of various revolutionaries abroad. The contents, reproduced in typed form, are unimportant and included primarily as examples of perlustration. Folder 2 has two dispatches referring to Burtsev's accusation censorship by the Okhrana in Paris and also two sets of letters addressed to revolutionary Rubanovich. Included with these is an expense account of principal agent Bint in Paris, charging five francs for each letter, possibly paid to the cooperating mail clerk. The items in Folder 3 include a set of original censored letters, Headquarters instructions to submit letters intercepted from Burtsev's mails, and an account of the scandal in Italy, where a postal employee was dismissed for delivering the mail of the revolutionaries to an Okhrana agent.
    Available on microfilm reel 142
    - Perlustrated letters of various revolutionaries abroad in Geneva, Paris, London, etc., 1903, 1905 (Index Xc, Folder 1)
      Marked in the Okhrana file as useless as intelligence sources.
    - Dispatches concerning censorship of mail in Paris and Burtsev's accusation in the press, 1914 (Index Xc, Folder 2a)
    - Perlustrated letters to Rubanovich, 1908 (Index Xc, Folder 2b)
    - Perlustrated letters, 1895-1908 (Index Xc, Folder 2c)
    - Intercepted letters from Moscow to Pontoise and from Montreaux to Switzerland, 1911-1913 (Index Xc, Folder 2d)
    - Various intercepted and perlustrated letters, 1884-1910 (Index Xc, Folder 3a)
    - Instructions about sending intercepted letters of Burtsev to Headquarters (Index Xc, Folder 3b)
    - Dispatches regarding the scandal with agents in the Italian post office, 1913 (Index Xc, Folder 3c)
    - Report from the Paris office concerning the establishment of a photographic darkroom for perlustration of correspondence, 1909 (Index Xc, Folder 3d)
    - Dispatch on the perlustration of Fundaminskii's mail, 1911 (Index Xc, Folder 3e)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index Xc, Folder 4)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 18, February 1, 1903, on the use of perlustrated correspondence of revolutionaries by the Okhrana offices, in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index Xc, Folder 5)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 22, February 28, 1903, on the use of information obtained from intercepted mail, in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index Xc, Folder 6)
    - Reference: See agent Pouchot's report on Leone's turning to Burtsev, in XXVIIa, folder 3 (Index Xc, Folder 7)
    - Reference: For complete sets of perlustrated mail addressed to Agafonov and Natanson, June 1908-March 1909, see XXIVa (Index Xc, Folder 8)
  - d. Graphological study of handwriting (Box 92)
    A number of small folders and enveloped were set aside in the original Okhrana files, marked as samples of handwriting and original signatures. The records do not reveal the assets or capabilities of the Paris Office in matters of graphological study, but some documents indicate that letters were submitted to it for analysis and identification of handwriting. The files also contain photographs of samples of handwriting.
    Available on microfilm reels 142-143
    - Perlustrated letters used as examples for the study of the handwriting of revolutionaries; samples of Burtsev's handwriting, 1905-1907 (Index Xd, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of handwriting samples of Trautman and an unidentified individual (Index Xd, Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 143
    - Samples of handwriting kept on file (Index Xd, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Zabrezhnev, submitted for analysis to the Paris Okhrana, 1905 (Index Xd, Folder 4)
    - Dispatches pertaining to graphological studies and identification of individuals through them, 1905-1914 (Index Xd, Folder 5)
  - e. Surveillance (Boxes 92-99)